Tonight, I'm going to try to make the case
هذه الليلة سأحاول إثبات أن
that inviting a loved one, a friend or even a stranger
دعوة حبيب أو صديق أو حتى أجنبي
to record a meaningful interview with you
لتسجيل مقابلة ذات معنى معك
just might turn out to be one of the most important moments in that person's life,
لربما تتحول لإحدى أجمل اللحظات في حياة ذلك الشخص
and in yours.
وحياتك.
When I was 22 years old, I was lucky enough to find my calling
عندما كنت في 22 من عمري كنت محظوظا كفاية لأجد حرفتي
when I fell into making radio stories.
عندما بدأت بإنشاء قصص إذاعية.
At almost the exact same time,
وفي ذات الوقت تقريباً،
I found out that my dad, who I was very, very close to, was gay.
اكتشفت أن أبي المقرب مني جداً كان مثلياً.
I was taken completely by surprise.
لقد باغتتني الدهشة تماما.
We were a very tight-knit family,
فقد كنّا عائلة مترابطة،
and I was crushed.
وقد كنت محطماً.
At some point, in one of our strained conversations,
يوماً ما وفي أحد حواراتنا الحادة،
my dad mentioned the Stonewall riots.
ذكر أبي اضطرابات ستونوول.
He told me that one night in 1969,
أخبرني أنه في ليلة من سنة 1969
a group of young black and Latino drag queens
قام جمع من الشباب السود ومتنكرون لاتينيون
fought back against the police at a gay bar in Manhattan
بزي نساء بصد الشرطة في حانة للمثليين بمنهاتن
called the Stonewall Inn,
تسمى نُزِل ستونوول.
and how this sparked the modern gay rights movement.
وكيف أن ذلك أشعل شرارة حركة حقوق المثليين الحديثة.
It was an amazing story, and it piqued my interest.
لقد كانت قصة رائعة استثارت حماستي.
So I decided to pick up my tape recorder and find out more.
فقررت حمل آلة التسجيل خاصتي لأبحث أكثر.
With the help of a young archivist named Michael Shirker,
وبمساعدة أمين أرشيف شاب يدعى مايكل شركر
we tracked down all of the people we could find
تتبعنا كل من استطعنا ممن كانوا
who had been at the Stonewall Inn that night.
حاضرين تلك الليلة في نزل ستونوول.
Recording these interviews,
وبتسجيل هذه المقابلات أدركت كم
I saw how the microphone gave me the license
أن الميكرفون أعطاني رخصة
to go places I otherwise never would have gone
للذهاب إلى أماكن لم أكن لأزورها
and talk to people I might not otherwise ever have spoken to.
والتحدث مع أشخاص ربما لم يكن بوسعي الحديث معهم مطلقاً.
I had the privilege of getting to know
لقد امتلكت امتياز التعرف على
some of the most amazing, fierce and courageous human beings
بعض أروع و أشرس و أشجع الشخصيات
I had ever met.
سبق لي مقابلتهم .
It was the first time the story of Stonewall
كانت المرة الأولى التي تُحكى فيها قصة
had been told to a national audience.
ستونوول للجمهور الوطني .
I dedicated the program to my dad,
أهديت البرنامج لوالدي،
Over the next 15 years, I made many more radio documentaries,
خلال 15 سنة قمت بعمل وثائقيات إذاعية كثيرة
working to shine a light on people who are rarely heard from in the media.
لألقي الضوء على المهمشين في الإعلام.
Over and over again,
ومرارا وتكرارا أرى كيف يعني هذا
I'd see how this simple act of being interviewed
العمل البسيط-أن تُجرى معك مقابلة-
could mean so much to people,
قد يعني الكثير للناس،
particularly those who had been told that their stories didn't matter.
وبالأخص لأولئك الذين قيل لهم أن قصصهم لا تعني شيئا.
I could literally see people's back straighten
استطعت حرفيا رؤية الناس يزدادون قوة
as they started to speak into the microphone.
عندما يبدأون التحدث للميكرفون.
In 1998, I made a documentary about the last flophouse hotels
و في سنة 1998 أجريت حلقة وثائقية عن الفنادق الرديئة
on the Bowery in Manhattan.
في شارع بوري بمنهاتن.
Guys stayed up in these cheap hotels for decades.
حيث أقام شباب بهذه الفنادق الرخيصة لعقود.
They lived in cubicles the size of prison cells
عاشوا في كبائن بحجم زنازين سجن
covered with chicken wire
مغطاة بسلك الدجاج المعدني
so you couldn't jump from one room into the next.
لتعجز عن القفز من غرفة لأخرى
Later, I wrote a book on the men with the photographer Harvey Wang.
ولاحقاً كتبت عنهم بالاشتراك مع المصور هارفي وانغ.
I remember walking into a flophouse with an early version of the book
أتذكر وأنا أخطو لفندق رديء بنسخة كتاب قديمة
and showing one of the guys his page.
وأنا أُري أحدهم صفحته.
He stood there staring at it in silence,
لقد وقف هناك يحدق فيها بصمت،
then he grabbed the book out of my hand
ثم انتزع الكتاب من يدي
and started running down the long, narrow hallway
ليهرب عبر الرواق الضيق الطويل
holding it over his head
حاملا الكتاب فوق رأسه
shouting, "I exist! I exist."
صارخاً ”أنا موجود، أنا موجود.“
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In many ways, "I exist" became the clarion call for StoryCorps,
أصبحت ”أنا موجود“ صرخة النداء لستوريكوربس
this crazy idea that I had a dozen years ago.
هذه الفكرة المجنونة التي حملتها 12 سنة.
The thought was to take documentary work
كانت الفكرة لتأخذ شكل عمل وثائقي
and turn it on its head.
يقلبها رأسا على عقب.
Traditionally, broadcast documentary
يقوم التوثيق تقليديا على تسجيل
has been about recording interviews to create a work of art or entertainment
مقابلات لإنشاء عمل فني أو مسل أو تعليمي
but I wanted to try something
لكني أردت تجربة شيء ما
where the interview itself was the purpose of this work,
حيث أن المقابلة نفسها هي الهدف من وراء العمل،
and see if we could give many, many, many people the chance
وكيف يمكننا أن نتيح هذه الفرصة لعد كبير جدا من الناس
to be listened to in this way.
ليتم الاستماع لهم على هذا النحو.
So in Grand Central Terminal 11 years ago,
قبل 11 سنة بغراند سينترال تيرمينال
we built a booth where anyone can come to honor someone else
بنينا كابينة يمكن لأي أحد أن يحتفي بآخر فيها
by interviewing them about their life.
عبر دعوته لإجراء مقابلة معه عن حياته.
You come to this booth and you're met by a facilitator who brings you inside.
ما أن تأتي للكابينة حتى تقابل وسيطا يدخلك.
You sit across from, say, your grandfather
تجلس بمواجهة ولنقل جدك لما يقارب الساعة
Many people think of it as, if this was to be our last conversation,
نظرة الكثير لها هي لو أن تلك كانت المحادثة الأخيرة
what would I want to ask of and say to this person
فما الذي أود سؤاله وقوله للشخص
who means so much to me?
الذي يعني لي الكثير ؟
At the end of the session, you walk away with a copy of the interview
وفي ختام الجلسة تنصرف برفقة نسخة
and another copy goes to the American Folklife Center
من المقابلة فيما تذهب أخرى لمركز الفلكلور الأمريكي
at the Library of Congress
في مكتبة الكونغرس ليستطيع
so that your great-great-great-grandkids can someday get to know your grandfather
حفيد حفيد حفيدك يوما ما أن يتعرف على جدك
through his voice and story.
من خلال قصته وصوته.
So we open this booth in one of the busiest places in the world
افتتحنا الكابينة بأحد أكثر الأماكن إزدحاماً في العالم
and invite people to have this incredibly intimate conversation
لندعو الناس لعقد هذه المحادثة الحميمية
with another human being.
مع إنسان آخر .
I had no idea if it would work, but from the very beginning, it did.
لم أملك فكرة عن النجاح لكنه من البداية حدث ذلك
People treated the experience with incredible respect,
وقد قُوبلت التجربة بتقدير جم
and amazing conversations happened inside.
وأجريت الكثير من المحادثات الرائعة .
I want to play just one animated excerpt
أود تشغيل مقتطفٍ متحرك من محادثة سُجلت
This is 12-year-old Joshua Littman interviewing his mother, Sarah.
هذا جشوا ليتمان وعمره 12 ، يجري مقابلة مع أمه سارا .
Josh has Asperger's syndrome.
إنه مصاب بمتلازمة أسبرجر.
As you may know, kids with Asperger's are incredibly smart
وتعلمون أن الأطفال المصابين بها هم غاية في الذكاء
but have a tough time socially.
ولكنهم يعانون اجتماعيا .
They usually have obsessions.
يعانون غالبا من الهواجس.
In Josh's case, it's with animals,
وفي حالة جوش نجد هذا مع الحيوانات.
so this is Josh talking with his mom Sarah
إذن إليكم جوش يتحادث أمه سارا
at Grand Central nine years ago.
قبل 9 سنوات في غراند سينترال.
(Video) Josh Littman: From a scale of one to 10,
(فيديو) جوش ليتمان: بمقياس 1 إلى 10
do you think your life would be different without animals?
هل كانت حياتك لتختلف دون الحيوانات؟
Sarah Littman: I think it would be an eight without animals,
أظنني سأختار 8 في مدى اختلاف حياتي دونها
because they add so much pleasure to life.
فهي تضيف الكثير من المتعة للحياة.
JL: How else do you think your life would be different without them?
ج ل:كيف ستبدو مختلفة أيضا دونها؟
SL: I could do without things like cockroaches and snakes.
س ل:ستبدو مختلفة ما عدا الصراصير والحيات.
JL: Well, I'm okay with snakes as long as they're not venomous
ج ل:حسنٌ،لا مشكلة لدي مع الحيات غير السمية
or constrict you or anything.
أو التي لا تقيد حركتي ونحوه.
SL: Yeah, I'm not a big snake person --
س ل:نعم، لست مولعة بالحيات--
JL: But cockroach is just the insect we love to hate.
ج ل:ولكن الصرصور أكثر حشرة يحلو لنا كرهها.
SL: Yeah, it really is.
س ل:صحيح، الأمر كذلك.
JL: Have you ever thought you couldn't cope with having a child?
ج ل:هل فكرت في عجزك عن التأقلم مع الأطفال؟
SL: I remember when you were a baby, you had really bad colic,
س ل:أذكر يوم كنت رضيعا أنك أصبت بغمص حاد
so you would just cry and cry.
وكنت تبكي دون توقف.
JL: What's colic? SL: It's when you get this stomach ache
ج ل:وما هو المغص؟ س ل:إنه ألم يصيب المعدة
and all you do is scream for, like, four hours.
و كل ما تملك معه أن تبكي ربما لأربع ساعات.
JL: Even louder than Amy does?
ج ل: وبأعلى من صوت آمي ؟
SL: You were pretty loud, but Amy's was more high-pitched.
س ل:كان صوتك عاليا لكن صوتها كان أكثر حدة.
JL: I think it feels like everyone seems to like Amy more,
ج ل:لدي شعور أن الجميع يحب آمي أكثر
like she's the perfect little angel.
كما لو أنها الملاك الصغير الكامل.
SL: Well, I can understand why you think that people like Amy more,
س ل:حسنٌ، أتفهم سبب ظنك أن الناس يميلون لها أكثر
and I'm not saying it's because of your Asperger's syndrome,
ولست أقول أن السبب أن لديك متلازمة أسبرجر،
but being friendly comes easily to Amy,
ولكن بسبب شخصيتها الودودة،
whereas I think for you it's more difficult,
بينما أظن أن الأمر صعب بالنسبة لك،
but the people who take the time to get to know you love you so much.
لكن من يُتاح لهم معرفتك عن قرب يحبونك كثيرا.
JL: Like Ben or Eric or Carlos? SL: Yeah --
ج ل:مثل بن و إريك و كارلوس؟ س ل: نعم--
JL: Like I have better quality friends but less quantity? (Laughter)
ج ل:أي أصدقاء بكم قليل وجودة عالية؟(ضحك)
SL: I wouldn't judge the quality, but I think --
س ل:ما كنت لأحكم على الجودة، لكني أعتقد--
JL: I mean, first it was like, Amy loved Claudia, then she hated Claudia,
ج ل:أعني في البداية أحبت آمي كلوديا ثم كرهتها،
she loved Claudia, then she hated Claudia.
أحبتها ثم كرهتها.
SL: Part of that's a girl thing, honey.
س ل:جزء من هذا يخص البنات، حبيبي.
The important thing for you is that you have a few very good friends,
الأهم أن لديك أصدقاء قليل فاضلون
and really that's what you need in life.
وهذا ما أنت بحاجة اليه في الحياة.
JL: Did I turn out to be the son you wanted when I was born?
ج ل:هل غدوت الطفل الذي تمنيتِه حال ولادتي؟
Did I meet your expectations?
هل كنت عند ظنونك؟
SL: You've exceeded my expectations, sweetie,
س ل:لقد تجاوزت كل ظنوني، حبيبي.
because, sure, you have these fantasies of what your child's going to be like,
بطبيعة الحال لكلٍ خيالاته عما سيكون عليه طفله،
but you have made me grow so much as a parent, because you think --
ولكنك جعلتني أنضج كوالدة، لأنك تظن--
JL: Well, I was the one who made you a parent.
ج ل:حسنٌ،أنا من جعلك تصبحين أما .
SL: You were the one who made me a parent. That's a good point. (Laughter)
س ل: أنت من جعلني أما. هذه نقطة جيدة.(ضحك)
But also because you think differently
ولأنك تفكر بشكل مختلف كذلك
from what they tell you in the parenting books,
ومن خلال ما أخبروني عنه في كتب الأبوّة،
I really had to learn to think outside of the box with you,
فقد وجب علي تعلم التفكير خارج الصندوق معك،
and it's made me much more creative as a parent and as a person,
وهذا ما جعلني أبدو أكثر إبداعا كأم وشخص،
and I'll always thank you for that.
وسأبقى أشكرك دوما لأجل هذا.
JL: And that helped when Amy was born?
ج ل: وهذا ساعدك حين وُلدت آمي؟
SL: And that helped when Amy was born, but you are so incredibly special to me
س ل:نعم . ولكنك عزيز علي للغاية
and I'm so lucky to have you as my son.
وأنا في غاية الحظ أن تكون ابنًا لي .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
David Isay: After this story ran on public radio,
ديفيد أسي: تلقى جوش مئات الرسائل بعد إذاعة
Josh received hundreds of letters
القصة على الراديو الوطني تخبره
telling him what an amazing kid he was.
كيف أنه كان طفلا رائعا.
His mom, Sarah, bound them together in a book,
قامت أمه ساره بجمعها في كتاب،
and when Josh got picked on at school, they would read the letters together.
وكانا يقرآنها حين يتم إزعاجه في المدرسة .
I just want to acknowledge that two of my heroes
أود التنويه بأن بطليَّ
are here with us tonight.
معنا هذه الليلة .
Sarah Littman and her son Josh, who is now an honors student in college.
سارا ليتمان وابنها جوش الجامعي المتفوق .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You know, a lot of people talk about crying when they hear StoryCorps stories,
يتحدث الكثير عن البكاء حين يسمعون قصص ستوريكوربس
and it's not because they're sad.
ليس لأنهم حزانى بطبعهم.
Most of them aren't.
معظمهم ليسوا كذلك.
I think it's because you're hearing something authentic and pure
وإنما لأنهم يسمعون شيئا صادقا ونقيا
at this moment, when sometimes it's hard to tell
في زمن من الصعب فيه أن تفرق
what's real and what's an advertisement.
بين الحقيقي والإعلان التجاري.
It's kind of the anti-reality TV.
شيئٌ ما على النقيض من تلفزيون الواقع.
Nobody comes to StoryCorps to get rich.
لا أحد يأتي لستوريكوربس كي يصبحا غنيا،
Nobody comes to get famous.
أو ليصبح مشهورا.
It's simply an act of generosity and love.
إنه ببساطة عملٌ مِن أعمال الكرم والحب.
So many of these are just everyday people
لهذا الكثير من هذه القصص لأناس عاديين
talking about lives lived with kindness, courage, decency and dignity,
يتحدثون عن حيوات عاشوها بطيبة وشجاعة، بعفة وكرامة،
and when you hear that kind of story,
وحين تسمع قصصا كهذه
it can sometimes feel like you're walking on holy ground.
يخامرك شعورٌ ما بأنك تخطو فوق أرض مقدسة.
So this experiment in Grand Central worked,
وهذا سبب نجاح تجربتنا بغراند سنترال،
and we expanded across the country.
وقد أتيح لنا الانتشار عبر البلاد.
Today, more than 100,000 people in all 50 states
واليوم فإن أكثر من 100,000 في 50 ولاية
in thousands of cities and towns across America
وفي آلاف المدن والبلدات في أمريكا
have recorded StoryCorps interviews.
قد قام كلهم بتسجيل مقابلات لدى ستوريكربس.
It's now the largest single collection of human voices ever gathered.
وأضحت أكبر مجموعة للأصوات البشرية بإطلاق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We've hired and trained hundreds of facilitators
وقد وظفنا ودربنا مئات الوسطاء
to help guide people through the experience.
لمساعدة الناس للقيام بهذه التجربة.
Most serve a year or two with StoryCorps
معظمهم خدموا لسنة أو سنتين مع ستوريكوربس
traveling the country, gathering the wisdom of humanity.
يقطعون البلاد لجمع حكمة البشرية.
They call it bearing witness,
يصفونها بحملٍ للشهادة ،
and if you ask them,
ولو أنك سألتهم ،
all of the facilitators will tell you that the most important thing
فسيجيب كل الوسطاء أن الأهم من كل ما تعلموه
they've learned from being present during these interviews
أثناء تسجيل المقابلات
is that people are basically good.
أن الناس جميعا صالحون من حيث الأصل.
And I think for the first years of StoryCorps, you could argue
وأظن أن لك أن تجادل أن ثمة انحياز
that there was some kind of a selection bias happening,
حصل نوعا ما خلال السنوات الأولى.
but after tens of thousands of interviews with every kind of person
بعد عشرات آلاف المقابلات مع كل أنواع الشخصيات
in every part of the country --
كل جزء من البلاد--
rich, poor, five years old to 105,
أغنياء، فقراء، من 5 سنوات إلى 105،
80 different languages, across the political spectrum --
80 لغة مختلفة عبر جميع الأطياف السياسية--
you have to think that maybe these guys are actually onto something.
عليك أن تفكر أن هؤلاء ربما يعون شيئا ما.
I've also learned so much from these interviews.
وكذلك تعلمت الكثير من هذه المقابلات.
I've learned about the poetry and the wisdom and the grace
تعلمت أشياء في الشعر والحكمة والإحسان
that can be found in the words of people all around us
والتي نجدها ربما في كلمات كل المحيطين بنا
when we simply take the time to listen,
بمجرد أن نملك الوقت لنستمع إليهم ،
like this interview
كهذه المقابلة
between a betting clerk in Brooklyn named Danny Perasa
بين موظف مراهنات في بروكلين يدعى داني بيراسا
who brought his wife Annie to StoryCorps to talk about his love for her.
والذي أحضر زوجته آني لستوريكوربس ليحدثها عن حبه لها.
(Audio) Danny Perasa: You see, the thing of it is,
(صوت)داني بيراسا: تعرفين ، القضية أني
I always feel guilty when I say "I love you" to you.
دوما أشعر بالذنب حين أقول لك عبارة ”أحبك“.
And I say it so often. I say it to remind you
أقولها مرارا. أفعل هذا لأذكرك أنها
that as dumpy as I am, it's coming from me.
تأتي مني ،أنا البدين القصير
It's like hearing a beautiful song from a busted old radio,
فتشبه سماع أغنية جميلة من مذياع قديم محطم.
and it's nice of you to keep the radio around the house.
ومن الجميل منك أن يبقى المذياع في المنزل.
Annie Perasa: If I don't have a note on the kitchen table,
آني بيراسا: لو لم يكن لدي ملاحظة على على طاولة المطبخ
I think there's something wrong.
لقلت أن ثمة خطأ.
You write a love letter to me every morning.
فأنت تكتب لي كل صباح رسالة حب.
is I couldn't find a silly pen.
آ ب:إلى أميرتي:
AP: To my princess:
السماء تهطل اليوم بغزارة.
I'll call you at 11:20 in the morning.
سأهاتفك في 11:20 صباحا.
DP: It's a romantic weather report.
د ب:إنها تقرير رومانسي عن الطقس.
AP: And I love you. I love you. I love you.
آ ب:ثم إني أحبكِ، أحبكِ ،أحبك.
DP: When a guy is happily married, no matter what happens at work,
د ب:حين تكون زوجا سعيدا، لا يهم ما سيحدث
no matter what happens in the rest of the day,
في عملك أو سائر اليوم
there's a shelter when you get home,
فثمة ملجأ حين تعود لمنزلك ،
there's a knowledge knowing that you can hug somebody
تعرف مسبقا أن هناك من تستطيع احتضانه
without them throwing you downstairs and saying, "Get your hands off me."
دون قذفك للطابق الأسفل صارخاً ”ارفع يديك عني“.
You never want to go back to black and white.
لست بحاجة لأن تعود للأبيض والأسود.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
DI: Danny was about five feet tall
د أ:كان طول داني حوالي الخمسة أقدام
with crossed eyes and one single snaggletooth,
بعيون حولاء ، وسنٍ ناتيء عن موضعه،
but Danny Perasa had more romance in his little pinky
لكن داني كان أكثر رومانسية من
than all of Hollywood's leading men put together.
كل رجال هوليوود مجتمعين.
What else have I learned?
وماذا تعلمت أيضاً؟
I've learned about the almost unimaginable capacity
لقد اطلعت تقريبا على المقدرة الخارقة
for the human spirit to forgive.
للنفس البشرية في أن تغفر.
I've learned about resilience and I've learned about strength.
واطلعت عَلى الليونة ، كما اطلعت على القوة.
Like an interview with Oshea Israel and Mary Johnson.
مثل مقابلة بين أوشي إسرائيل و ماري جونسون
When Oshea was a teenager, he murdered Mary's only son,
فقد قتل أوشي وهو مراهق ابن ماري الوحيد
Laramiun Byrd, in a gang fight.
لاراميون بير في مشاجرة عصابات.
A dozen years later, Mary went to prison
وبعد 12 سنة ذهبت ماري للسجن
to meet Oshea and find out who this person was
كي تقابل أوشي ولتعرف من يكون ذلك الشخص
who had taken her son's life.
الذي انتزع حياة ابنها .
Slowly and remarkably, they became friends,
وبطريقة بطيئة وملفتة للنظر أصبحا صديقين،
and when he was finally released from the penitentiary,
وحين أُطلق سراحه وخرج من الإصلاحية
Oshea actually moved in next door to Mary.
في النهاية جاور أوشي بيت ماري.
This is just a short excerpt of a conversation they had
هذا مقتطف بسيط من محادثة جرت بينهما
soon after Oshea was freed.
عقب إطلاق سراح أوشي مباشرة.
(Video) Mary Johnson: My natural son is no longer here.
(فيديو) ماري جونسون: ابني الحقيقي لن يكون
I didn't see him graduate, and now you're going to college.
هنا للأبد. لم أره يتخرج، وأنت ستدرس الجامعة.
I'll have the opportunity to see you graduate.
سيكون بوسعي أن أراك تتخرج.
I didn't see him get married.
لم أره يتزوج.
Hopefully one day, I'll be able to experience that with you.
ويحدوني الأمل أن أجرب رؤيتك تتزوج.
Oshea Israel: Just to hear you say those things and to be
أوشي :أن أسمعك تنطقين هذه الأشياء وأن
in my life in the manner in which you are is my motivation.
تكوني في حياتي كما أنت الآن لهو دافع
It motivates me to make sure that I stay on the right path.
يدفعني لأن أكون على يقين أني على الطريق
You still believe in me,
مازلتِ تؤمنين بي،
and the fact that you can do it despite how much pain I caused you,
وأن تملكي القدرة على ذلك برغم حجم الألم الذي سببته لك
it's amazing.
لهو أمر مذهل.
MJ: I know it's not an easy thing to be able to share our story together,
م ج: ليس سهلا كما أعرف أن نتشارك قصتنا معاً
even with us sitting here looking at each other right now.
ولو جالسين ننظر في عيون بعضنا الآن.
I know it's not an easy thing, so I admire that you can do this.
ليس سهلا كما أعرف ويعجبني أن تستطيع ذلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
DI: And I've been reminded countless times of the courage and goodness of people,
د إ: ذُكّرت كثيرا بشجاعة الناس و استقامتهم،
and how the arc of history truly does bend towards justice.
وكيف أن قوس التاريخ ينحني بحق صوب العدالة.
Like the story of Alexis Martinez, who was born Arthur Martinez
كقصة أليكسس مارتنز؛ المولودة بمشاريع هارولد
in the Harold Ickes projects in Chicago.
آيكز بشيكاغو بصفتها آرثر مارتنز.
In the interview, she talks with her daughter Lesley
تتحدث في المقابلة مع ابنتها ليسلي
about joining a gang as a young man,
عن انضمامها لعصابة كشاب،
and later in life transitioning into the woman she was always meant to be.
ثم تحولها جنسيا للمرأة التي طالما تمنت.
This is Alexis and her daughter Lesley.
هذه أليس وابنتها ليسلي.
to be in my granddaughters' lives,
في حياة حفيدتي،
and you blew that completely out of the water,
لكنك سحقتِ هذا الوهم تماما،
you and your husband.
أنتِ و زوجك.
One of the fruits of that is, in my relationship with my granddaughters,
وإحدى ثمرات هذا هي علاقتي بحفيداتي.
they fight with each other sometimes over whether I'm he or she.
حيث يتشاجرن أحيانا بسببي وهل أنا هو أم هي.
Lesley Martinez: But they're free to talk about it.
ليسلي: لكن لديهن الحرية في التحدث عن هذا.
AM: They're free to talk about it, but that, to me, is a miracle.
أ م: يملكن ذلك، لكن ذلك معجزة بالنسبة لي.
LM: You don't have to apologize. You don't have to tiptoe.
ل م:ليس عليك الاعتذار أو القلق.
We're not going to cut you off, and that's something I've always
لن نحجبكِ ، وهذا شيء كنت دائما
wanted you to just know, that you're loved.
أريد أن تعلميه، أنكِ محبوبة.
AM: You know, I live this every day now.
أ م:إني أعيش الآن حالتي الجنسية كل يوم،
I walk down the streets as a woman, and I really am at peace with who I am.
أمشي في الشوارع كامرأة، في سلام مع نفسي.
I mean, I wish I had a softer voice maybe,
تمنيتُ أن لدي صوت أكثر نعومة ربما،
but now I walk in love and I try to live that way every day.
ولكن الآن أمشي بحب، و أحاول عيش هذه الطريقة يوميا.
DI: Now I walk in love.
د إ: إني أمشي بحب.
I'm going to tell you a secret about StoryCorps.
سأخبركم سرًا عن ستوريكوربس.
It takes some courage to have these conversations.
الأمر يحتاج إلى بعض الشجاعة لإجراء هذه الحوارات.
StoryCorps speaks to our mortality.
إننا في ستوريكوربس نحادث الفناء.
Participants know this recording will be heard long after they're gone.
فنحن نعلم أن التسجيل سيُسمع بعد الرحيل.
There's a hospice doctor named Ira Byock
هناك طبيب بدار عجزة اسمه إرا بيوك،
who has worked closely with us on recording interviews
وقد عمل معنا عن قرب في تسجيل بعض المقابلات
with people who are dying.
مع بعض من كانوا يحتضرون.
He wrote a book called "The Four Things That Matter Most"
ألف كتابا أسماه ”أهم أربعة أمور“
about the four things you want to say to the most important people in your life
عن أربعة أمور تود قولها لأهم الناس من في حياتك
before they or you die:
قبل أن تموت أو يموتوا:
thank you, I love you,
شكرًا، أحبك،
forgive me, I forgive you.
سامحني، سامحتك.
They're just about the most powerful words we can say to one another,
إنها أقوى الكلمات التي نود قولها لبعضنا،
and often that's what happens in a StoryCorps booth.
وعادة هذا ما يحدث في كبينة لستوريكوربس.
It's a chance to have a sense of closure with someone you care about --
هي فرصة امتلاك معنى النهاية مع من يهمك --
no regrets, nothing left unsaid.
لا ندم، لا شيء لم يُقل.
And it's hard and it takes courage,
وهو أمر صعب ، ويحتاج قدرًا من الشجاعة،
but that's why we're alive, right?
لكن هذا السبب في أن نعيش الآن، أليس كذلك؟
So, the TED Prize.
و جائزة TED؟
When I first heard from TED and Chris a few months ago
حين سمعت من TED و كريس قبل أشهر إمكانية
about the possibility of the Prize, I was completely floored.
الحصول على الجائزة، أخذني الذهول من الفرحة.
They asked me to come up with a very brief wish for humanity,
طُلب مني الإتيان بأمنية قصيرة للبشرية،
no more than 50 words.
لاتزيد عن 50 كلمة.
So I thought about it, I wrote my 50 words,
فكرت في الأمنية، و كتبت 50 كلمة.
and a few weeks later, Chris called and said, "Go for it."
وبعد أسابيع هاتفني كرس قائلا: ”أسعى خلفها.“
So here is my wish:
وهاهي أمنيتي:
that you will help us
أنك سوف تساعدنا
take everything we've learned through StoryCorps
في أن نجعل كل شيء تعلمناه في ستوريكوربس
and bring it to the world
متاحاً للعالم،
so that anyone anywhere can easily record a meaningful interview
ليستطيع أي شخص في أي مكان تسجيل مقابلة ذات معنى
with another human being which will then be archived for history.
مع أي إنسان بسهولة كي يمكن أرشفتها للتاريخ.
How are we going to do that? With this.
كيف سيكون بوسعنا فعل ذلك؟ بهذا (هاتف).
We're fast moving into a future where everyone in the world
نمشي بوتيرة متسارعة لمستقبل يستطيع فيه
will have access to one of these,
كل أحد الوصول لأحد هذه ،
and it has powers I never could have imagined 11 years ago
وبإمكانيات لم أتخيلها مطلقا قبل 11 سنة
when I started StoryCorps.
حين أسسنا ستوريكوربس.
It has a microphone,
به ميكرفون ،
it can tell you how to do things,
يخبرك ما ينبغي عليك فعله،
and it can send audio files.
كما يمكنه إرسال الملفات الصوتية.
Those are the key ingredients.
هذه هي الوصفات الأساسية.
So the first part of the wish is already underway.
إذن القسم الأول من الأمنية قد تحقق.
Over the past couple of months,
عبر الأشهر القليلة الماضية
the team at StoryCorps has been working furiously
لقد كان فريق ستوريكوربس يعمل بشدة
to create an app that will bring StoryCorps out of our booths
لأجل بناء تطبيق يُحضر لك كبائن ستوريكوربس
so that it can be experienced by anyone, anywhere, anytime.
كي يجربها كل أحد في كل زمان و مكان.
helping them record their conversation, which is preserved forever,
يساعدهم في تسجيل محادثتهم كي تحفظ للأبد،
but at this very moment,
لكننا نطلق في هذه اللحظة
we're releasing a public beta version of the StoryCorps app.
نسخة تجريبية عامة لتطبيق ستوريكوربس.
The app is a digital facilitator that walks you through
التطبيق وسيط رقمي يسير بك خلال
the StoryCorps interview process,
آلية المقابلة لستوريكوربس،
helps you pick questions,
يساعدك في اختيار الأسئلة ،
and gives you all the tips you need
مع إعطائك كل ما تحتاجه من إرشادات
to record a meaningful StoryCorps interview,
في تسجيل محادثة ذات معنى لستوريكوربس،
and then with one tap upload it to our archive at the Library of Congress.
وبضغطة يمكنك رفعها لأرشيف مكتبة الكونغرس.
That's the easy part, the technology.
و الجزء السهل هنا هو التقنية .
The real challenge is up to you:
التحدي الحقيقي يعود لك أنت:
to take this tool and figure out how we can use it
أن تأخذ هذه الأداة وتعرف طريقة استعمالها
all across America and around the world,
عبر طول البلاد وأرجاء العالم ،
so that instead of recording thousands of StoryCorps interviews a year,
و عوضا عن تسجيل آلاف المقابلات سنوياً
we could potentially record tens of thousands
في ستوريكوربس، من المحتمل أن نسجل عشرات الآلاف
or hundreds of thousands
وربما مئات الآلاف،
or maybe even more.
وربما أكثر من هذا.
Imagine, for example, a national homework assignment
ولتتخيل مثلا تكليفاً وطنياً منزلياً
where every high school student studying U.S. history across the country
يقوم به كل طلاب الثانوية الدارسين للتاريخ الأمريكي عبر البلاد
records an interview with an elder over Thanksgiving,
بتسجيل مقابلة مع مُسنّ خلال عيد الشكر،
so that in one single weekend
بحيث يمكن في إجازة نهاية أسبوع واحدة
an entire generation of American lives and experiences are captured.
تقييد حيوات وتجارب جيل أمريكي كامل.
Or imagine mothers on opposite sides of a conflict somewhere in the world
أو تخيل الأمهات على قبالة جانبي الصراع في مكان ما في العالم
but to find out who they are as people,
ولكن بمعرفة أنفسهن كبشر،
and in doing so, begin to build bonds of trust;
وبصنعيهن هذا يشرعن في بناء جسور من الثقة،
or that someday it becomes a tradition all over the world
أو أن يوما ما يصبح تقليداً في كافة أنحاء العالم
that people are honored with a StoryCorps interview
أن يتم تكريم الناس بمقابلة في ستوريكوربس
on their 75th birthday;
في عيده ميلادهم الـ75
or that people in your community
أو أن يذهب الناس في مجتمعك
go into retirement homes or hospitals or homeless shelters or even prisons
لدور العجزة أو مشردي الملاجيء أو السجون حتى
armed with this app to honor the people least heard in our society
مسلحين بهذا التطبيق للاحتفاء بالناس المهمشين في مجتمعنا
and ask them who they are, what they've learned in life,
والسؤال عنهم وعما تعلّموه في الحياة
and how they want to be remembered.
وكيف يريدون أن يُذكروا بعد رحيلهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Ten years ago, I recorded a StoryCorps interview with my dad
أجريت قبل 10سنوات مقابلة ستوريكوربس مع أبي
who was a psychiatrist, and became a well-known gay activist.
الذي كان طبيبا نفسيا وناشطا مثليا معروفا.
This is the picture of us at that interview.
هذه صورتنا في تلك المقابلة.
I never thought about that recording until a couple of years ago,
لم أفكر في هذه المقابلة حتى سنوات قليلة،
when my dad, who seemed to be in perfect health
حين كان بصحة طيبة
and was still seeing patients 40 hours a week,
وكان لا يزال رؤية المرضى 40 ساعة في الأسبوع،
was diagnosed with cancer.
وفجأة أثبت التشخيص إصابته بالسرطان.
He passed away very suddenly a few days later.
وبعدها بأيام كان رحيله المفاجيء.
It was June 28, 2012,
في 28 يونيو،2012.
the anniversary of the Stonewall riots.
كانت الذكرى السنوية لاضطرابات ستونوول
I listened to that interview for the first time at three in the morning
استمعت لتلك المقابلة للمرة الأولى في الثالثة صباحا،
on the day that he died.
في يوم رحيله.
I have a couple of young kids at home,
لدي مجموعة من الأبناء الصغار في المنزل
and I knew that the only way they were going to get to know this person
أدركت أن الطريقة التي بها فقط يمكنهم
who was such a towering figure in my life would be through that session.
معرفة هذا الرمز الشامخ هي تلك الجلسة.
I thought I couldn't believe in StoryCorps any more deeply than I did,
و أدركت أنني أعجز عن الإيمان بستوريكوربس بعمق أكثر مما فعلت.
but it was at that moment
وفي تلك اللحظة فقط
that I fully and viscerally grasped the importance of making these recordings.
أدركت تماما وبعمق أهمية هذه التسجيلات.
Every day, people come up to me
يقابلني الناس كل يوم ليقول أحدهم:
and say, "I wish I had interviewed my father or my grandmother or my brother,
”ليتني أجريت مقابلة مع أبي أو جدتي أو أخي،
but I waited too long."
لكنني انتظرت طويلًا جدا.“
Now, no one has to wait anymore.
لكننا لا يجب أن ننتظر بعد الآن.
At this moment,
ففي هذه اللحظة ،
when so much of how we communicate is fleeting and inconsequential,
التي تمتليء بتواصلنا العابر وغير الهام،
join us in creating this digital archive
فلك أن ترافقنا في إنشاء هذا الأرشيف الرقمي
of conversations that are enduring and important.
لمحادثات خالدة ذات أهمية.
Help us create this gift to our children,
ساعدنا في عمارة هذه الهدية لأطفالنا،
this testament to who we are as human beings.
هذه الوصية لنا نحن البشر.
I hope you'll help us make this wish come true.
يحدوني الأمل أن تعيننا لنحقق هذه الأمنية.
Interview a family member, a friend or even a stranger.
أجر مقابلة مع أحد عائلتك، أو صديق أو غريب.
Together, we can create an archive of the wisdom of humanity,
إننا نملك أن ننشيء أرشيفا لحكمة البشرية،
and maybe in doing so,
ولو فعلنا ذلك ،
we'll learn to listen a little more and shout a little less.
لربما تعلمنا كيف نستمع أكثر من أن نصرخ.
Maybe these conversations will remind us what's really important.
ربما تذكرنا هذه المحادثات بما هو مهم.
And maybe, just maybe,
وربما، أقول ربما
it will help us recognize that simple truth
سوف تساعدنا في التعرف على الحقيقة البسيطة
that every life, every single life,
وهي أن كل حياة ، نعم كل حياة
matters equally and infinitely.
ذات أهمية متساوية وبلا حدود.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم شكرًا جزيلا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرًا لكم ، شكرًا .
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)